A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, M-R FA393
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Russell, Frederick F.
  Russell continued his career in applied medical research following his retirement from the RF in 1935; that year the National Academy of Sciences awarded him the Public Welfare Medal. For the next four years he served as a professor of epidemiology and preventive medicine at Harvard University. Frederick F. Russell died at the age of 90 in 1960.
  - 1922-1924 (Box 417)
  - 1925-1926 (Box 418)
  - 1927-1930 (Box 418)
  - 1931-1935 (Box 418)
- Russell, Harry Luman
  Harry Luman Russell (1866-1954) was an American bacteriologist and educator. Russell was graduated from the University of Wisconsin in 1884, received an M.S. from Wisconsin in 1890, and a Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins in 1892. Russell then became a Professor at the University of Wisconsin. In 1903 Russell was made Director of the Wisconsin State Hygienic Laboratory, and became Dean of the University of Wisconsin's College of Agriculture in 1907. Russell was also a charter member of the American Society for Microbiology, and was named President in 1908. In 1925 Russell was commissioned by the International Education Board (IEB) to travel through Asia, and survey the scientific and agricultural education needs in Japan, China, the Philippines, Siam, Java, Australia, and New Zealand.
  Harry Luman Russell's logs (diaries) document his 1925-1926 trip through Asia, and survey the scientific and agricultural education needs in Japan, China, the Philippines, Siam, Java, Australia, and New Zealand.
  Indexing to Harry Luman Russell's logs is provided by the International Education Board records, Albert R. Mann and Harry Luman Russell logs index (FA769).
  Agriculture -- Philippines; Agriculture -- China; Agriculture -- Australia; Agriculture -- Japan; Agriculture -- New Zealand
  - Vol. I: Japan, 1925-1926 (Box 419)
    Includes maps and photographs.
    Includes: Tokyo, Sapporo (Hokkaido), Sendai (Tohoku University), Kyoto, Fukuoka (Kyushu University), and Special Reports: Prefectural experiment stations; Prospective candidates for IEB travelling professorships; Japanese "Hakase" in comparison with American Ph.D. requirements; Forestry in Japan; Fisheries in Japan; Science in Japan; Agriculture in Japan; Marine biological laboratories.
  - Vol. II: China and Philippines, 1926 (Box 419)
    Includes -- China: Peking, Shanghai, Nanking, Amoy and Canton, and Special Reports: General report on China; Mass education movement in China; Problem of returned student in China; Collatoral organizations interested in research.
    Philippines: Present status of requests received from the Far East transmitted by Dean H.L. Russell.
    Agriculture -- China; Agriculture -- Philippines
  - Vol. III: Siam, Java, Australia, 1926 (Box 420)
    Includes -- Siam: Bangkok, General educational situation in Siam.
    Java: Batavia, Buitenzorg, Bandoeng, Bangalan, Malang, Pasoeroean, Klaten; Report on the Javanese situation.
    Australia: Perth, Adelaide, Roseworthy, Melbourne, Tasmania, Sydney, Brisbane, Canberra, and Special reports: Possible candidates for IEB fellowship; Australian Council for Scientific and industrial Research, Forestry in Australia, Endowment of science research in Australia; Agricultural science and education in Australia; Veterinary science in Australia; Australian universities and general science development.
    Agriculture -- Asia.
  - Vol. IV: New Zealand, Hawaii, Summary, and Index of Orient Trip, 1926 (Box 420)
    Includes -- New Zealand: Dunedin, Christchurch, Lincoln, Nelson, Wellington, Auckland, and Special Reports: Fellowship possibilities in New Zealand; Agricultural education and research in New Zealand; Higher education in New Zealand with special reference to natural research; Forestry in New Zealand.
    Hawaii: Special reports: Fellowship possibilities in Hawaii; General situation in the Hawaiian Islands.
    Summary regarding applicability of IEB fellowship plan to Pacific countries visited in 1926.
- Russell, Paul F.
  Asia
  - 1938, Russell, Paul F.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 71 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 1)
    In the 1938 diary of Russell, he investigates and researches Malaria in his Madras laboratory. The bulk of the diary includes his daily research measurements of mosquito densities. An experiment research report is included.
    Diaries; India; Malaria; Public health
  - 1939, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 79 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 72)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He continues his investigations on malaria research with an emphasis on mosquito control. A trip to the Netherlands is taken to learn information on malaria relating to his research. The diary includes "Statement Regarding Potential Malariousness of the New Site for the University of the Philippines, Quezon City, Luzon."
    Public health; Philippines; Malaria; India; United States; Singapore; Diaries; Holland (Netherlands: Province)
  - 1940, Russell, Paul F.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 81 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 151)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He continues his investigations on malaria research with an emphasis on mosquito control. Malaria studies include measurements of spleen and blood indices as well as capture of larvae and adult mosquitoes. Field studies at various sites in India include experiments with spray killing mosquitoes, and the correlation between irrigation and malaria.
    Diaries; Agriculture; Medicine -- Research; Malaria; Irrigation; India; Rice; Public health
  - 1941, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 82 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 233)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He continues his investigations on malaria research with an emphasis on mosquito control. Malaria studies include measurements of spleen and blood indices, mosquito densities, as well as capture of larvae and adult mosquitoes. Field studies at various sites in India include experiments with spray killing mosquitoes, and the correlation between irrigation and malaria. Includes, "Agenda of a conference at Pattukkottai Field Station of Malaria Investigations."
    Malaria; Medicine -- Research; Diaries; India; Irrigation; Public health; Rice; Agriculture
  - 1942, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 11 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 315)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He continues his investigations on malaria research with an emphasis on mosquito control. Included in this brief diary is the agenda for a conference in Tungabhadra. Russell returns from India to the United States to take a leave of absence from the Rockefeller Foundation for the duration of World War II.
    India; Diaries; United States; Malaria; Public health
  - 1946 November-December, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 26 pages (Reel M Rus 1, Frame 326, Box 421)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. As he returns from military service, Russell is assigned to Venezuela to carry on RF IHD malaria research. The RF IHD has been invited by the Government of Venezuela to undertaken malaria studies in cooperation with its Division of Malariology with a combined research program.
    Diaries; United States; Venezuela; Malaria; Public health
  - 1947, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 92 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 352)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He returns to the United States from Venezuela to obtain information regarding other various malaria studies and research investigations. Topics of effect of DDT spraying on malaria mosquitoes are discussed.
    Diaries; United States; Venezuela; Malaria; Public health; DDT (Insecticide)
  - Index, 1948; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F. (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 444)
    1948 Index; ten pages.
    Public health; indexes (reference sources); Malaria
  - 1948, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 197 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 454)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences and visits with professionals in the field of malaria research. Throughout the year, Russell's focus is on gathering research by reading research reports, field trial studies, manuscripts, diaries and papers.
    Public health; United States; Malaria; Medicine -- Research; DDT (Insecticide); Diaries; Chemotherapy
  - Index, 1949; Russell, Paul F.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 651)
    1949 Index; thirteen pages.
    Public health; Malaria; indexes (reference sources)
  - 1949, Russell, Paul F.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 222 pages (Box 421, Reel M Rus 1, Frame 664)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences and visits with professionals in the field of malaria research. He visits various countries in South American, Europe and the Middle East to assess local malaria research, outbreaks and discuss public health infrastructure. Russell continues to read various research studies and publications regarding malaria.
    Brazil; Cyprus; DDT (Insecticide); Diaries; Egypt; Irrigation; Italy; Malaria; Medicine -- Research; Middle East; Public health; Sardinia (Italy); Turkey; United States
  - 1950, Russell, Paul F.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 131 pages (Reel M Rus 2, Frame 1, Box 421)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences and visits with professionals in the field of malaria research. This diary documents malaria investigations and control in Vera Cruz, studies of control methods of vectors of disease and training local health department personnel in Malaria prevention. Russell visits various field sites, continues to work on his Malaria manuscript and attends the 37th Annual Meetings of the new Jersey Mosquito Extermination Association.
    Diaries; United States; Malaria; Medicine -- Research; Mexico; Public health; DDT (Insecticide); Italy
  - 1951, Russell, Paul F.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 152 pages (Reel M Rus 2, Frame 130, Box 421)
    1951 Index; nineteen pages organized according to persons, places and general index.
    1951 Trip Index; five pages organized according to place.
    1951 General Index; eight pages organized according to institutions, disease, drugs, insecticides and larvicides, insects, plasmodia, DMPH programs, projects, proposed projects, professional societies, schools of public health-USA, PFR books, PFR manuscripts, publishers.
    1951 Index of Persons; nineteen pages.
    1951 Index of Places; five pages.
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences, visits with professionals in the field of malaria research, and attends malaria tours. He is stationed at the RF Italy Office and is involved with the Sardinia-ERLAAS campaign to eradicate the labranchiae mosquito to effectively eliminate malaria from the area. Russell works on his manuscripts, and goes on a malaria tour of Congo and Greece.
    Italy; Malaria; Diaries; Medicine -- Research; Public health; DDT (Insecticide); Greece; Switzerland; Sardinia (Italy); United States
  - 1952, Russell, Paul F.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 178 pages (Reel M Rus 2, Frame 289, Box 422)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences, visits with professionals in the field of malaria research, and attends malaria tours. He works on his malaria book and lectures, and attends the 5th World Health Assembly.
    England; Family planning; DDT (Insecticide); Medicine -- Research; Population; Italy; Malaria; Sardinia (Italy); Spain; Portugal; Public health; Switzerland; Diaries; World Health Organization
  - 1953, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 71 pages (Reel M Rus 2, Frame 464, Box 422)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences, visits with professionals in the field of malaria research, and attends malaria tours. He works on his manuscript and attends the 5th WHO Expert Committee on Malaria Meeting in Istanbul.
    Turkey; France; India; England; Public health; Diaries; Switzerland; Italy; Malaria; World Health Organization
  - 1954, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 72 pages (Box 422, Reel M Rus 2, Frame 540)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences, visits with professionals in the field of malaria research, and attends malaria tours. He attends the 7th World Health Assembly and is appointed WHO medical consultant.
    Malaria; Public health; Diaries; World Health Organization
  - 1955, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 55 pages (Box 422, Reel M Rus 2, Frame 612)
    Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences and visits with professionals in the field of malaria research. He visits a DDT manufacturing plant in India, attends Pakistan's first malaria conference, works on his manuscripts and attends the 8th World Health Assembly as WHO consultant. Russell assesses countries by population density, areas of malaria outbreak and healthcare response. The international focus of the Rockefeller Foundation is eradicating malaria.
    United States; Diaries; Turkey; Lebanon; Malaria; Mexico; Pakistan; England; India; Iran; Iraq; Sri Lanka; Public health; Syria; Switzerland; World Health Organization
  - 1956, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; World Health Organization; Russell, Paul F.; 25 pages (Box 422, Reel M Rus 2, Frame 667)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences and visits with professionals in the field of malaria research. Russell works on manuscripts, lectures and papers with a focus on Malaria eradication. He also attends WHO sponsored conferences on malaria.
    Diaries; United States; Public health; Malaria; Italy
  - 1957, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F.; 34 pages (Reel M Rus 2, Frame 692, Box 422)
    As a staffer for the RF's International Health Division, Russell's diary is arranged according to interview and visit. He holds interviews, conferences and visits with professionals in the field of malaria research. Russell reports on various projects that are connected with Malaria research, meets with the World Health Organization and attends a meeting on malaria research of Laboratory Tropical Diseases, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.
    England; Malaria; Public health; Switzerland; United States; Diaries; World Health Organization
  - 1958, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F. (Reel M Rus 2, Frame 726, Box 422)
  - 1959, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Russell, Paul F. (Box 422, Reel M Rus 2, Frame 750)